Finding Aid for Paul Gordon Goebel Papers, 1942-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Paul Gordon Goebel papers 1942-1964
Goebel, Paul Gordon, 1901-
851303 Aa 2; UAm
Businessman and Republican mayor of Grand Rapids, Michigan, 1950-1954 and 1956-1958, delegate to the 1961 constitutional convention, and regent of University of Michigan. Correspondence, mayoral topical files, campaign materials, and scrapbooks concerning his activities in opposition to the political leadership of Frank D. McKay and George Welsh, the Republican National Convention of 1960, the work of the constitutional convention, and the founding of WZZM-TV and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
11 linear feet
1 oversize folders
The collection was the gift of Paul G. Goebel (donor no. 4451 ) and came to the library in 1966.
The collection is open to research.
Paul G. Goebel was born May 28, 1901 in Grand Rapids, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1923 with a degree in mechanical engineering. At the university, Goebel played football (All-American, 1922). In the coming years, Goebel would be an active alumnus, serving on the University's Board of Control of Intercollegiate Athletics and the National Board of Directors of the U-M Alumni Association. He was also elected as Republican to the University's Board of Regents, serving from 1962 to 1970. As Regent, Goebel also served as chairman of the $55 Million Campaign, a fund drive held in conjunction with the University's sesquicentennial celebration.
Goebel was a businessman and public servant active in Republican Party affairs. He was a reformist mayor of Grand Rapids, serving from 1950 to 1954 and 1956 to 1958. In addition, he was a delegate from Michigan's 16th senatorial district to the state constitutional convention, 1961-1962.
He died in January 26, 1988 in Grand Rapids, Michigan.
The Paul G. Goebel papers include correspondence, mayoral topical files, campaign materials, and scrapbooks concerning his activities in opposition to the political leadership of Frank D. McKay and George Welsh, the Republican National Convention of 1960, the work of the constitutional convention, and the founding of WZZM-TV. A small file of photographs consists of portraits, campaign photographs, and photos of Goebel at public functions The series in the collection include Correspondence; Mayoralty Papers; Personal and Political; Scrapbooks; Constitutional Convention; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Grand Rapids (Mich.); Mayors--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; McKay, Frank D., 1883-; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Municipal government--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Republican National Convention (27th: 1960: Chicago, Ill.); Republican Party (Mich.); Welsh, George Wilson, 1883-1974.; WZZM-TV (Television station: Grand Rapids, Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Mayors--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Political elections.; Voting.
Contributors:
Alger, Frederick Moulton, 1907-1967.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence 1950-1958
  - 1950-June 1957, 47 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1957-April 1958 (Box 2)
- Mayoralty Papers 1950-1954
  - Topical File 1950-1954
    - Appointments to city offices and boards, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Assessments, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Auditorium, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Budget, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Capitol Improvements (Box 2)
    - Charter Commission 1952, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - City Manager Applications 1953, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Consultants (Box 2)
    - County Budget, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Election 1950, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Election 1954, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Election 1954, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Elections-General, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Finances, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Foster Foundation (Box 3)
    - Gambling (Box 3)
    - Grand Rapids Motor Coach Company, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Highway (Box 3)
    - Housing, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Legal Opinions (Box 3)
    - Legislation (Box 3)
    - Library (Box 3)
    - Licenses (Box 3)
    - Liquor (Box 3)
    - Michigan Municipal league, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Officiating (Big Tea football games) (Box 4)
    - Parking, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Pensions (Box 4)
    - Personal, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Personnel, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Planning, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Public Relations (Box 4)
    - Radio (Box 4)
    - Rent Control, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Salaries, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Salaries, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Sewage Disposal, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Sinking Fund (Box 5)
    - Surveys (Box 5)
    - Taxes, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Television (Box 5)
    - Traffic (Box 5)
    - US Mayors Trip to the Middle East, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Water, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Y.M.C.A., 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Zoning, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Other Mayoralty Papers
    - Notebook on Planning 1950 (Box 5)
    - Budget Requests 1949-1950 (Box 5)
    - Election 1958, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Kent-Ottawa Metropolitan Water Authority, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 7 folders (Box 6)
    - Report on Prostitution in Grand Rapids (Box 6)
    - City Budgets and Financial Reports 1948-1957 (Box 6)
    - Hospital Study, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - Water Supply Design Report, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - Sewage Disposal Reports, 3 volumes (Box 7)
    - Parking Study, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - Urban Renewal Program, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - Airport Study, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - Civic Center Study, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - Downtown Grand Rapids Study, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - Grand Rapids Metropolitan Area Study, 7 volumes (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Publications, 7 volumes (Box 7)
- Personal and Political
  - Navy and Naval Reserve service, 16 folders (Box 7)
  - Republican Home Front Organization 1946-1949 (Box 7)
  - Recall campaign against Mayor George Welsh 1949 (Box 7)
  - Politics 1959-1964, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Republican National Convention 1960 (Box 7)
  - Gerald Ford for Vice-President Committee 1960 (Box 7)
  - Peninsular Broadcasting Company and WZZM-TV
    - Undated (Box 7)
    - 1962 (Box 7)
    - 1963 (Box 7)
    - 1964 (Box 7)
    - 1965 (Box 7)
- Scrapbooks 1942-1954
  (microfilm copy of scrapbooks also available)
  - Scrapbook 1942-1944 (Republican Home Front) (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook 1948-1949 (Republican Home Front) (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook April-June 1949 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook June 1949 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook June-November 1949 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook November 1949-January 1950 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook January-February 1950 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook February-April 1950 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook April-June 1950 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook June-July 1950 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook July-October 1950 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook October 1950-January 1951 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook January-June 1951 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook June-November 1951 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook November 1951-March 1952 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook March-October 1952 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook October 1952-February 1953 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook February-March 1953 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook March-May 1953 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook May-August 1953 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook August-October 1953 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook October 1953-January 1954 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook January-February 1954 (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings March-June 1954, 8 folders (Box 9)
- Constitutional Convention File 1961-1962
  - Taxation and Finance Committee Notebooks, 5 volumes (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous papers and correspondence (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks (Box 11)
- Photographs
  - Portraits, campaign photographs, and photos of Goebel at public functions, 3 folders (Box 11)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)
Selective Index of Correspondents
Alger, Frederick Moulton, 1907-1967.
Correspondence throughout
Ford, Gerald R., 1913-
Letter, June 7, 1952 from Clare Hoffman to Gerald R. Ford; Correspondence, 1956-1958 (throughout)
Letter, Jan. 23, 1963 (Con-Con files); Note: There is also material about Ford in the Goebel scrapbooks, in the Ford for V.P. file, and in the Republican Rome Front material
Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.
Letter, June 7, 1952, from Hoffman to Gerald R. Ford concerning Goebel.